<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christian race a sermon preach'd before the Queen at Kensington on Sunday the 31th of July, 1692 / by Richard Lucas ...</title>
            <author>Lucas, Richard, 1648-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49384</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3394</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13000</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13134807</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13134807</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97899</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49384)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97899)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 426:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christian race a sermon preach'd before the Queen at Kensington on Sunday the 31th of July, 1692 / by Richard Lucas ...</title>
                  <author>Lucas, Richard, 1648-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 26, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published by Her Majesties special command"</note>
                  <note>Advertisements: [2] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Hebrews XII, 1 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97899:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97899:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Chriſtian Race: A SERMON Preach'd before the QUEEN AT KENSINGTON, ON <hi>Sunday</hi> the 31<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>July,</hi> 1692.</p>
            <p>By <hi>RICHARD L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CAS</hi> D. D. Vicar of St. <hi>Stephens Coleman-ſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Her Maieſties Special Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Smith</hi> at the <hi>Princes Arms</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97899:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97899:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Chriſtian Race:</hi> Deliver'd in a SERMON Preach'd before the QUEEN at <hi>Kenſington,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>HEBR. xii. 1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Wherefore, ſeeing we alſo are compaſſed about with ſo great a Cloud of Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, let us lay aſide every weight, and the ſin which doth ſo eaſily beſet us, and let us run with patience the Race that is ſet before us.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>TO confront Atheiſm with the Reſurrection of Jeſus, and Immorality with the Lives of Saints, demonſtrating the Power of God in the one, and of Faith in the other, is a way of arguing, which if it do not Reclaim the Infidel and Sinner, if it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97899:3"/>do not utterly ſilence the Objections of the one againſt the Truth, and of the other againſt the Poſſibility of Religion, muſt yet needs ruffle and diſturb the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of both, and fill it with an uneaſie Shame and Fear; but how much more muſt this way of Reaſoning pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail wherever there are any Principles of Natural Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, or any Seeds of Ingenuity and Probity; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever there is but a <hi>Form of Godlineſs,</hi> or the leaſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the Power of it. This is the Method the Apoſtle here obſerves, he demonſtrates the Force and Virtue of Faith by the inſuperable Courage and Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of ſuch in all Ages as were acted and ſupported by it: And then well knowing, that the Belief of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Life was eſtabliſhed upon a brighter Revelation and fuller Evidence than God had ever yet vouchſafed the World, addreſſing himſelf to Chriſtians, as Men who would be aſhamed to be out-done by Jew or Gentile, or ſhrink at ſuch Trials as they had triumphed over, he concludes in the words of my Text, <hi>Wherefore, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we alſo are compaſſed about with ſo great a Cloud of Witneſſes,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Theſe words contains three Parts:
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>A Duty.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>Directions for the ſucceſsful diſcharge of it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. <hi>Motives and Inforcements to it.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Duty</hi> is, To <hi>run the Race that is ſet before us:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Direction</hi> conſiſts of Three Rules: 1. That we <hi>muſt lay aſide every weight;</hi> but eſpecially, 2ly, <hi>The ſin that doth ſo eaſily beſet us.</hi> 3ly, That we muſt <hi>run with patience.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97899:3"/>
            <p>The <hi>Motives</hi> and <hi>Inforcements</hi> are partly expreſſed in theſe words, <hi>Seeing we are compaſſed about with ſuch a Cloud of Witneſſes;</hi> partly implied and involved in the Metaphorical Deſcription of our Duty, <hi>The Race that is ſet before us;</hi> for this intimates a Crown to be the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of him, who ſo runs as to obtain.</p>
            <p>Firſt of the <hi>Duty:</hi> The Race of the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians conſiſted eſpecially in the Propagating the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Jeſus, and ſecuring their own by Sufferings and Blood. And that this is the Race my Text immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly relates to, is plain; it being nothing elſe but an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation founded on the Trials and Tortures in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Chapter,</hi> and reinforced by the Example of Jeſus in this, <hi>Who for the Joy that was ſet before him, indured the Croſs, and deſpiſed the Shame.</hi> But if we take this Exhortation in the utmoſt latitude we may, and ſuppoſe it addreſs'd to all Chriſtians in general, then our <hi>Race</hi> will conſiſt in <hi>doing the good which God hath appointed us,</hi> and eſpecially in <hi>ſurmounting whatever difficulty or oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition we may encounter in the purſuit of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. In <hi>doing Good:</hi> The great deſign of Chriſtianity is to multiply our Obligations and Incouragements, and to raiſe and inlarge our Capacities of doing good. The Holy Scripture was inſpired and written that the <hi>Man of God might be perfect, throughly furniſhed to every good work,</hi> and the Holy Spirit is communicated, to relieve the Weakneſſes and Indiſpoſitions of our Natures, and inable us to act the great things which that preſcribes. Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination fills the Mind of Man with a juſt comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Dignity of his Nature, and the great ends of his Creation. Purification ſets him at liberty to purſue them, and fires the Heart with a holy Ardour and Zeal to do ſo: and Faith ſtrengthens and fortifies him againſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97899:4"/>the contradiction of Sinners and Temptations of the Body. Doing good then is undoubtedly that wherein the Chriſtian Race conſiſts. But it muſt be</p>
            <p n="2">2ly, <hi>That Good</hi> which God hath <hi>appointed us.</hi> We muſt neither <hi>contract</hi> nor <hi>inlarge</hi> the Notion of doing good beyond thoſe Bounds which God hath ſet us. We muſt not inlarge it, by placing Religion in thoſe Works which Prejudice or Prepoſſeſſion, Fancy or Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Luſt or Paſſion, not God preſcribes: Nor may we break in upon the Rights, or invade the Offices of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, out of a deſign of doing good. Purity of Intention will hardly expiate Raſhneſs and Preſumption; nor will any Good attain'd, compenſate the Miſchiefs flowing from an Example of ſo much Injuſtice and Confuſion; nor is it therefore to be wondred at, if ſuch a one meet with the Puniſhment of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zza,</hi> not the Crown of St. <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as we muſt not inlarge, ſo we muſt not <hi>contract</hi> the Notion of doing Good. To which end I muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark to you, That it conſiſts not only, 1. in reſcuing the Wretched and Unfortunate from Temporal, or, 2. the Fool and Sinner from Eternal Evil, <hi>i. e.</hi> in root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out Vice and Errour, and propagating Truth and Vertue, concerning both which there can be no doubt; but alſo, 3ly, In the due Diſcharge of the Duties of Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Stations or Callings. The Reaſon of this is plain; they are all, from the higheſt to the loweſt, in a true and proper ſenſe, appointed of God; they do miniſter to excellent ends, and proceed from, and are conducted by excellent Principles, <hi>Faith in God,</hi> and <hi>Conformity to his Providence;</hi> and then no wonder if Humility, Faith, and Purity of Intention, tranſmute Civil into Religious A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, as the <hi>Elixir</hi> of <hi>Adepts</hi> is ſaid to do inferiour Mettals into Gold. Hence it is that the <hi>ſubduing King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:97899:4"/>and <hi>working Righteouſneſs,</hi> which in the <hi>Ideom</hi> of the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> ſignifies the protecting and deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the People of God, the <hi>waxing valiant in fight,</hi> and <hi>putting to flight the Armies of the Aliens,</hi> are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded by the Apoſtle <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11. not only as the Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick Exploits of <hi>Gideon,</hi> and <hi>Baruch, Jepththa,</hi> and <hi>Sampſon</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> but as truly and properly Acts of Faith, as the Sacrifice of <hi>Abel</hi> or <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Ark of <hi>Noah,</hi> or the Flight of <hi>Moſes.</hi> And hence <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. the Induſtry and Faithfulneſs of Servants is interpreted, as truly Religion towards God, as Service towards Man, and this upon a ground that Miniſters Incouragement to Men of all Conditions and Profeſſions, knowing that <hi>whatſoever good a Man doeth, the ſame he ſhall receive of God, whether he be bond or free:</hi> all this put together, as it furniſhes us with a juſt Notion of the Chriſtian Race, ſo does it with a juſt one of Chriſtianity it ſelf; he derogates from it, who forms any other <hi>Idea</hi> of it than this, That it is a moſt effectual and comprehenſive Deſign of advancing all the good Mankind is capable of. As it has its Vertues which adorn the Man, ſo has it thoſe too which adorn the Prince, the General, the Judge, and ſo downwards. As it hath its Vertues which perfect and accompliſh <hi>Human Nature,</hi> ſo has it thoſe too which cement and ſupport <hi>Civil Society:</hi> It is is ſo far from conſiſting in Modes and Forms, in Heats and Enthuſiaſm, that it conſiſts not in Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation it ſelf alone; <hi>laying aſide every weight, and the ſin that doth ſo eaſily beſet us,</hi> is in my Text but a Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification or Preparation to the <hi>running the Race ſet before us.</hi> Whoever then confines Religion to Private and Solitary Piety, I mean to ſuch a one as is uſeleſs to the World, diſſolves the Vigour, and impoveriſhes the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97899:5"/>Generoſity of the Chriſtian Spirit. Godlineſs and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety without Righteouſneſs, would make but a maim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and imperfect Religion; for it is not the Deſign of Religion to reſolve Societies and Kingdoms into <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits</hi> and <hi>Monks,</hi> but to purifie and raiſe them, and make the <hi>Kingdoms of the World the Kingdoms of our Lord, and of his Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a Deſign ſo glorious, ſo benign and gracious, that one would think, whoeſer ingages in it, ſhould find every thing eaſie and yielding, propitious and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>favourable to him. But alas! if he conſider the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of Nature, the Malice of Hell, and Degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the World, he has reaſon to expect a very for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable Oppoſition. In the Conqueſt of which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts</p>
            <p>The Third and moſt conſiderable Part of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Race. <hi>My Son,</hi> ſaid <hi>Jeſus</hi> the Son of <hi>Sirach, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticus</hi> the 2d <hi>Chapter,</hi> and <hi>verſes</hi> 1, 2. <hi>if thou come to ſerve the Lord, prepare thy Soul for Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſet thy heart aright, and conſtantly endure, and make not haſte in time of trouble.</hi> Which, if we ſhould ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him to ſpeak Prophetically, will amount to thus much, Whoever thou art who reſolveſt to enter the Liſts of Chriſtianity, and <hi>run the Race that is ſet before thee,</hi> dream not of a cheap and eaſie Victory, thou ſhalt be encountred with violent Oppoſition from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and from without. Sloth, or Self-preſervation, will ſolicite thee to eaſe and reſt, why ſhouldſt thou <hi>be righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous over much,</hi> and deſtroy thy ſelf? why ſhouldſt thou exchange thy calm and ſecurity of a quiet private Piety, for the ſtorms and troubles in which thy Zeal and Raſhneſs will imbroil thee? Diffidence or Diſtruſt in God, Impatience under thy own Fortune, or Envy
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97899:5"/>of anothers, will ſuggeſt to thee many more effectual and compendious ways to Honour and Intereſt, than a conſcientious, <hi>i. e.</hi> a tame and toilſome diſcharge of Duty. Senſuality, or at leaſt Lukewarmneſs, will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to perſwade, that it is a Supream point of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to reconcile the Hopes of another World with the Pleaſures and Enjoyments of this; to which if thou liſten thou art undone. For this is a Perſwaſion which ſhoots a dead Palſie through the very Sinews of Zeal, clips the Wings, and takes down the Sails of Charity. Nor ſhalt thou be leſs diſtreſt from without, then from within; the Squadrons of Hell will beſet thee round, and Enemies will fall on from every Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; there will be <hi>Sadducees</hi> and <hi>Atheiſts</hi> that will At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taque thy Faith, and tear up, if they can, thy Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs by the Roots: There will be <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> who will blaſte thy good Actions, and aggravate thy Infirmities, either out of hatred to the Communion thou art off, or which is worſe, a cloſe and ſecret A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to all Religion. There will not be wanting <hi>Hobbiſts</hi> and <hi>Herodians, Machivilians, Craftsmen,</hi> and innumerable others, who will Aſſault thy Religion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in Zeal and Charity; ſome as Folly, others as a Scandal and Offence; ſome as Enemy to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and others as Enemy to Trade. For an humble, modeſt, and a frugal Religion, will not fail of being Traduced, as menacing the Trade as much as the Sin of a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and as impairing the Revenues, while it prunes the Luxury of a State. Reformation, though it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed a vicious World, as the Angel did <hi>Betheſda's</hi> Water, only to work Cures, yet ſhall it never eſcape the Rallery and Reflections, the ſmall and great Shot of the Looſe and Immoral; and whatever Meaſures it
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97899:6"/>take, whether it revive old Conſtitutions, or recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend new, ſhall ever be branded as Deſign and Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, by all ſuch as thrive and grow fat by Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing the Laws of God and Man. Nay more yet, there will not be wanting Advocates of Vice, or Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Vertue, in thine own Train and Family, who will dehort thee from all expenſive and hazardous Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, and indeavour to divert thee, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> would have done our Saviour from the Paths which lead to Trials or Sufferings, to <hi>Gethſemane</hi> or <hi>Golgotha.</hi> Finally, to compleat the Politicks of Hell, thou ſhalt find the World divided into Factions, Religious and Civil, who will ſtamp Vice on the moſt glorious Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Honour and Vertue on Extravagancies and Debaucheries, who will perſecute the Truth of God as Hereſie and Novelty, and ſtickle for the Tenets, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Intereſt of their Parties, as for the Fundamentals of Faith, or Precepts of the Decalogue. And after all, God himſelf ſometimes will withdraw, and ſeem to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon and give thee up to the Will of wicked Men, ſo that thou ſhalt be ready to cry out with his beloved Son, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me.</hi> Here is the Trial, here is the Patience of the Saints. Theſe and many more are the Difficulties thou art to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, if thou wilt <hi>ſo run as to obtain;</hi> and therefore prepare thy ſelf by Mortification and Diſcipline, and fortifie thy Soul by the wiſeſt Advice, and the moſt powerful Incouragements, for thou ſhalt have need of all.</p>
            <p>This minds me of my Second General Direction for the Diſcharge of this Duty, conſiſting of Three Rules. I begin with the firſt, that is, <hi>to lay aſide every weight,</hi> every corrupt Affection, which like a weight would clog and retard us in our Race.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:97899:6"/>
            <p>This Advice contains ſeveral important Truths, as Firſt, That whatever the Diſorder or Depravation of Nature be, which we derive from our firſt Parents, our Deſtruction is from our ſelves; and thoſe Reluctan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and Averſions for Righteouſneſs, to which we owe our Ruin, are rather contracted, then Original. 'Tis true, there is a Law in the Body which wars againſt the Law of the Mind; but then it is as true, that there is a Law in the Mind, which wars againſt the Law of the Body. The Language of the Body is indeed more ſoft and inſinuating, but that of the Mind more au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoratative and awful. The Body, like <hi>Eſau,</hi> is the Firſt-born; for as <hi>Job</hi> obſerves, <hi>Man is born like a wild Aſſes Colt;</hi> but the Mind, like <hi>Jacob,</hi> comes into the World with a better Title by Divine deſignation, and a Capacity which ſoon defeats it of its uſurped Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Birthright. The Objects finally of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy are preſent and ſenſible; yet to the Soul, the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Eternity of its Objects make amends for their diſtance and futurity, and Faith Supplies the place of Viſion; for Faith is <hi>the Subſtance of things hoped for, the Evidence of things not ſeen,</hi> Hebr. 11.1. So that 'tis evident, the Scale of Victory is not turned on the ſide of the Body againſt the Mind, till falſe Principles have ſupplanted the Authority of the one, and Indulgence and ill Cuſtoms increaſed and fortified the Propenſions of the other to worldly and ſenſible things. I have remarkt this, that none of us may go about to remove the Guilt of our Ruin from our ſelves on our firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, or God, that none may think we have ſufficiently diſcharged our Duty by accuſing our Nature, or excuſed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97899:7"/>our Vices by Arraigning our Frailty. This calls to mind a</p>
            <p>Second Truth contained in this Rule, namely, That no Sin is invincible, that none is ſo deeply rooted in us, either by Nature or Cuſtom, but it may be extirpated. This is an Aſſertion you will eaſily admit, if you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider by what glorious Inſtruments the Converſion of Man is wrought, the Spirit of God, and the Word of God, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Wiſdom and the Power of God. Or if you conſider the Deſcription of it in Holy Scripture; it is called <hi>the Divine Nature, the New Creature, the Image of God, the Life of Faith,</hi> a being <hi>transformed from Glory to Glory, the glorious Liberty of the Sons of God,</hi> and ſuch like. What Degrees of Perfection all this may import, I enquire not; 'tis plain it can im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply nothing leſs than a Purification from all Filthineſs of Fleſh and Spirit, and through Sanctification of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Soul and Body. Nor is this a matter of meer Speculation; the Converts of the firſt Times, were living Demonſtrations of this Truth; and their daily Actions were nothing elſe but the glorious Effects of an intire Victory, not over the Weakeſt only, but moſt Obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of their Sins. All this inculcates this one plain Leſſon, That no Man muſt think to ſhelter his Negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and Lukewarmneſs, or any Darling Luſt, under the pretence of an inſuperable Infirmity; or that by owning himſelf to be but Man, he is excuſed from being a Chriſtian. The truth is, if Chriſtianity did conſiſt in a Quarrel, only with our Sins, not a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of them, it would be nothing elſe but a Circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Sins and Follies; for Regret and Remorſe,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97899:7"/>which doth only diſturb, not reform, may be reckoned amongſt the Infirmities of Man, and that Repentance which brings not forth Fruit, is it ſelf to be repented of amongſt our other Faults. For,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The laſt Truth I'le obſerve to you from this Rule, is, That Spiritual Liberty is the beginning of Perfection; that the firſt ſtep towards doing Well, is ceaſing to do Evil; that the Chriſtian muſt make the firſt Experiment of his Zeal upon himſelf; that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and Charity muſt begin at home: not only that his Attempts of doing good, may have in them their proper Luſter and Majeſty, their juſt Authority and Influence; but indeed that he may be qualified and capacitated for making any: for how weak and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucceſsful muſt his Endeavours be, whilſt ſome wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Luſt takes up his time, imployes the Vigour of his Soul, and alienates his Affection from every thing that is truly Great or Good. Will the Unclean deny the Importunities of his Luſt, to ſatisfie thoſe of his Duty? will the Covetous impoveriſh himſelf, (ſo he ſtyles gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Alms) to ſupport others in Lazineſs, and yet his Heap of Treaſure, like heaps of Soil and Dung, is good for nothing till it is ſcattered abroad? Will the Proud ſtoop to the humble Offices which our Crucified Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour did? will the Soft or the Ambitious run thoſe Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards, or indure thoſe Hardſhips which are generally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable in carrying on any conſiderable Good? or will the Factious croſs the Intereſt of his Party to promote that of his God, I mean that of Religion in General? This abundantly demonſtrates how inconſiſtent every ſinful Affection is with Succeſs in our Chriſtian Race,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97899:8"/>and conſequently how neceſſary the Advice of my Text is, That we ſhould put it off as a burthen or weight. Nor is this true only of this or that particular Sin, but of all in general, and therefore me muſt put off <hi>every weight. Strive,</hi> ſaid our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>to enter in at the ſtreight Gate; for ſtreight is the Gate, and narrow is the way that leadeth unto Life, and few there be that find it.</hi> All our vigour, all our ſtrength, aſſiſted by the Spirit of God, will be little enough to open this Way, and ſtorm Heaven. Ah! what can we expect from Affections divided between God and Mammon, or any other Luſt? from Strengths ſcattered and diſperfed in purſuit of Vice as well as Vertue? and theſe deſerted and abandoned by the Spirit of God; for <hi>the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Diſcipline will fly Deceit, and will not abide when Iniquity cometh in,</hi> Wiſd. 1.</p>
            <p>But though all Sin in general obſtruct the Chriſtian in his Race, and defeat him of his Crown, yet none ſo fatally as the beloved one: And therefore 'tis againſt <hi>this,</hi> againſt <hi>the ſin that eaſily beſets us,</hi> that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in his ſecond Rule awakens all our Jealouſie, and Summons all our Courage; this being the Sin in which eſpecially lyes the ſtrength of Satan, and in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of it the firſt, and I think I may add the greateſt Difficulty of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>To illuſtrate therefore this Advice of the Apoſtle, I'le firſt ſhew what it is, and then ſecondly, how to cure it.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:97899:8"/>
            <p>Firſt, What it is; As in the Humours of the Body, ſo in the Vices of the Mind, there is one Predominant, which is this, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it has an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendant over us, and leads and governs us; it is in the Body of Sin, what the Heart is in the Body of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; it begins to live firſt, and dies laſt; and whilſt it lives it communicates Life and Spirit to the whole Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Sin, and when it dies, the Body of Sin expires with it. It is the Sin to which our Conſtitutions leads, our Circumſtances betray, and Cuſtom inſlaves us; the Sin to which, not our Vertues only, but Vices too, lour their Topſail and ſubmit; the Sin, which when we would impoſe upon God and our Conſciences, we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe and diſguiſe with all imaginable Artifice and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry; but when we are ſincere with both, we op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe firſt and conquer laſt. 'Tis, in a word, the Sin which Reigns and Rules in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregenerate,</hi> and too often Alarums and Diſturbs, ah, that I could ſay no more, the <hi>Regenerate!</hi> Having thus fully diſcovered what this Sin is, without vexing and torturing the Text by Criticiſins, I'le now proceed ſecondly, to ſhew you how to conquer it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Indeavour to poſſeſs your Souls with a true Notion of Sin in General, but eſpecially of this beloved one in Particular; Falſhood and Folly, Levity and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy. Cowardize and Ingratitude, and all that is baſe, conſtitute the very Eſſence of Sin. As to the Effects of it, it diſhonours, and as much as in it lies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrones God, diſturbs and embroyls Human Society, depraves Nature, perverts the true ends of Life; and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97899:9"/>for all theſe Reaſons will one day bring down all the Storms of Eternal Vengeance upon the Guilty and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent Soul.</p>
            <p>This is a true Notion of Sin in general, and let no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ever tempt us to ſofter Thoughts of our <hi>beloved</hi> Sin: The ſame baſeneſs gives it being, and though its Effects may not be ſo injurious, as thoſe of ſome other Sins, either to the Honour of Religion, or the Intereſt of Man, yet they will be no leſs fatal to <hi>thee.</hi> This Sin is like ſome Diſeaſes, which though they ſeem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible in themſelves, are always deadly to ſome Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies and Conſtitutions: But can that be a little Sin, which creates us the greateſt Trouble, Threatens us with the greateſt Danger, and Intangles us in the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Difficulties? Is that a little Sin which has ſo often overthrown our Solemn Vows and Reſolutions, robbed us of our Peace and Hopes, and fill'd our Souls with Remorſe and Shame? Is that a Sin to be deſpiſed which the weightieſt Reaſons, the cleareſt Convictions, and warmeſt Impreſſions of the Spirit do often fail to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer? Is that finally a Sin to be ſhelter'd and excuſed which bewailed, condemned, renounced, deteſted, baffled, broken, routed, often r'allies and renews the fight, and recovers for a time its former Dignity and Authority? Certainly, did we Morning and Evening ſeriouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon the ſtrength and miſchief of this our favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite Sin, of which each Man ought to have a Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue by him, we ſhould, whenever tempted to it, tremble and grow pale at the Temptation, and fly back with the horrour of <hi>Joſeph, How ſhall I do this great wickedneſs, and ſin againſt God?</hi> But after we have done
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97899:9"/>all this, we muſt take as much pains to preſerve, as we did to imprint this Notion in our Souls; we muſt not ſuffer our Reaſon to vary with our Pulſe, and our Reſolutions to change with our Company, Fortune, Temper, Humour; otherwiſe we ſhall ſoon pull down in an Hour of Gaiety, what we built up in many ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ones, and a fit of Pleaſure and Jollity will deprive us in a moment of the Fruit of many Prayers, Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Meditations. And becauſe we are very lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to this, therefore</p>
            <p>Secondly, We muſt frequently renew our Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt it: And theſe Reſolutions muſt <hi>first</hi> be le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled, not only againſt this Sin, but all Appearances of, and Approaches to it. What is Cruelty in Princes, is Piety in Penitents; the Expreſſion of our Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure muſt light, not only on the Criminal it ſelf, but on all its Friends and Relatives. We muſt deal with this Sin as <hi>Iſrael</hi> was obliged to do with Idols, not only reduce the Idol it ſelf to Aſhes, and bury it in a Stream of Repentant Tears, but cut down its Groves, dig up his Altars, ſlay its Prieſts, and deface what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever might tend to preſerve or revive the memory of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Theſe Reſolutions muſt be as well fitted to all Occaſions and Circumſtances as poſſible we can; we muſt conſider what Arts, what Arms this Sin is wont to make uſe of, where our Nature or our Vertue is weakeſt, or moſt expoſed to the Aſſaults of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; we muſt in one word, neither be ignorant of any Frailty of our own, nor any wile of the Devil, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97899:10"/>then our Reſolutions muſt be ſo formed, as to obviate each. Is my Temper Raſh and Precipitate, Light and Inconſtant? I muſt reſolve to correct it by the Awe of the Divince Preſence, by Meditations, on Death and Judgment. Is it ſlow, heavy and unapprehenſive? I muſt reſolve to awaken it by Retirement and Prayer; by entring often into an impartial view of my own ſtate; by Converſation, if I can find that it hath warmth and ſpirit in it; by the moſt pathetick portions of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Writ, and by a frequent Recollection of all thoſe Truths which have Edge and Point in them, or at leaſt have ſo to me. Is this Sin wont to dart its Infection through the Eye? Is it wont to wound or defile us by the Ear? we muſt block up theſe Avenues of Death and Damnation; we muſt guard the Soul, as God did Paradiſe with the flaming Sword of an Angel; with that awful Vertue and inflamed Zeal, that Temptations may fly from before us. Thus muſt we, in a word, oppoſe Art againſt Art, and Force againſt Force, and in our Spiritual Warfare imitate the Wiſdom of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of this World, who count it unpardonable Errour to be often impoſed on by the ſame Artifice, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed by the ſame Methods. After all, you muſt bind theſe Reſolutions on your Souls, by Prayer and Sacraments, and this one particular Conſideration,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly.</hi> That nothing leſs than the Conqueſt of this darling Sin can gain a Chriſtian true Peace and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. While we retain a Sin that Rivals God in our Affection, neither our Obedience nor Aſſurance can be ſincere or conſtant; we can have no pleaſure in our Reflection on our ſelves, nor confidence in our Addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to God. No Man is ſo wicked, as to be inclined
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97899:10"/>to all ſins, nor ſo fooliſh, as to quit none; 'tis therefore the quitting the <hi>predominant</hi> Sin, which is the beſt proof of our Integrity; with <hi>others,</hi> we part, as with Civil Acquaintances, when the Viſit is done; but with <hi>theſe,</hi> as with Confidents and Friends, or in the Language of our Saviour, with our <hi>right Hands,</hi> or our <hi>right Eyes.</hi> But when this is done, our Freedom and Pleaſure will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſate our Trouble; and Hope, and Joy, reward our Mortification. But then we muſt take care that we finiſh, as well as we begin and compleat that Chriſtian Race in Patience, which we began in Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification. Which brings me to my third Rule, That we muſt run with <hi>Patience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Rule will contain two or three Things: 1. A Suppoſition or Inſinuation that ſuch as ſtand may fall; that ſuch as run may faint and grow weary, and ſo forfeit their Crown.</p>
            <p>All the Promiſes which God makes his People of his Preſence and Protection in their Dangers and Trials, are deſigned to miniſter Incouragement to the Humble and the Watchful, and muſt not be perverted to nouriſh Confidence and Security, or to defeat that Humility, Vigilance, and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection which the Spirit of God in Scripture endeavours, by repeated Exhortations, to beget in every Chriſtian. Our Saviour indeed, when he tells his Diſciples, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.24. That <hi>there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets;</hi> and then adds, That <hi>they ſhall ſhew great ſigns and wonders, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97899:11"/>that if it were poſſible, they ſhall deceive the very Elect;</hi> ſeems plainly to imply, that it was not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; but then, without flying to the diſtinction between the <hi>Faithful</hi> and <hi>Elect,</hi> made uſe of indeed by St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and ſome others of the Fathers, whether ſufficiently founded in Scripture, or no, I determine not; without flying, I ſay, to this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, this Text may eaſily be reconciled with thoſe which ſuppoſe the poſſibility of a Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Man's Revolt from Vertue; for it is very obvious to any one, that our Saviour ſpeaks not here of the Perſeverance of this or that particular Perſon, but of the Continuance or Preſervation of the Chriſtian Church, aſſerting no more here then what he had done before, <hi>That the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt it.</hi> 'Tis true indeed, ſome of the Ancients thought that there was a Height or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence of Holineſs, which when Man had arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at, he was raiſed above the poſſibility of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. I examine not what Countenance this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion had from Holy Scripture, becauſe 'tis, if an Errour, I think at leaſt an harmleſs one; for the more holy, the more humble; the nearer to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, the more fervent and watchful. But I'le not intangle my ſelf in this Matter, ſince all I intend to build upon this Doctrine, is only <hi>that</hi> Caution and Circumſpection, which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture every where exhorts Chriſtians to, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly here in my Text.</p>
            <p>Now the Advice of Patience referring to <hi>that</hi> Oppoſition which the Chriſtian is to Encounter
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97899:11"/>from within and from without, we may reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably conceive it to inculcate theſe two Things: 1. That we ſhould watch carefully over our ſelves; 2. That we ſhould bear the ſhock, and on-ſet of the World with Conſtancy and Courage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That we ſhould Watch, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Since he that ſtands may fall, let no Man preſume too ſoon of an intire Conqueſt, nor grow Secure or Careleſs, as if paſt the reach of Danger. When we have put off every old Sin, the Seeds of new ones will remain till we put off the Body; we muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore continue our Guard and Watch, and uſe as much diligence to keep the Enemy under, as we did at firſt to ſubdue it. It is a wiſe Example St. <hi>Paul</hi> hath ſet us, who continued the ſame Diſcipline over the Body which he began with; <hi>I keep under the Body, and bring it in ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, leaſt at any time when I preach to others, I my ſelf may become a Caſt-away.</hi> It often happens in the Chriſtian as is doth in Secular Wars, that he loſes the Fruit of a dear bought Victory, who makes too much haſte to enjoy it. If therefore you will be ſafe, you muſt not be ſecure; be not too ſoon confident of a Reconciliation with God, nor too haſty to calm the Sorrows, and ſtill the Agonies of an afflicted Conſcience; the more laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Grief is, the more intire and compleat will be the Victory; the more wakeful and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous thy Soul is, the more firm will be thy Peace. In this caſe too forward Joy is like a too forward Spring, whoſe early Bloſſoms ſeldom
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97899:12"/>come to Maturity and Perfection. Nay, I muſt put you in mind, That when the Seaſon of this Fruit is come, <hi>i. e.</hi> when Tribulation has wrought Patience, Patience Experience, Experience Hope, Hope raiſed high on the Wings of Love, Hope inebriated by the Joy of the Holy Ghoſt, we muſt even then follow the Advice of the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, <hi>Serve the Lord with fear, and rejoyce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him with trembling.</hi> Even then our Zeal muſt increaſe with our Hope, and our Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection and Humility with our Spiritual Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; even then, as if our Work and Duty did increaſe with our Strength and Capacity, as if the difficulteſt Task of our Chriſtianity was ſtill behind, or all that we have hitherto done would amount to nothing, if we did not hold out with Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Courage to the Goal. We muſt immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the great Apoſtle of the <hi>Gentiles, Brethren, I count not my ſelf to have apprehended, but this one thing I do, forgetting thoſe things which are behind, and reaching forth unto thoſe things which are before, I preſs toward the Mark for the Prize of the high Calling of God which is in Christ Jeſus,</hi> Phil. 3.13, 14.</p>
            <p>And you will ſee this very reaſonable, if you conſider what this Rule ſuggeſts in the <hi>ſecond</hi> place, namely, That we are to meet with much Oppoſition from the World, which we muſt bear manfully; nor will theſe Trials have an end, but with our Lives; nay, often the ſharpeſt are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, like Martyrdom, for our laſt Moments:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97899:12"/>Therefore the Scripture every where inculcates, That we ſhould not look on Chriſtianity as a ſtate of Senſuality; or project to our ſelves the Pleaſure and the Honour, the Eaſe and Intereſt of Life; but Hardſhips and Labour, Watching, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and War: whence it was our Lord did adviſe his Auditors, that before they followed him, they ſhould conſider what they undertook, as wiſe Builders do their Fund before they begin to build, or wiſe Princes their Strength and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion before they ingage in a War. 'Tis true, the taking up the Croſs in a litteral Sence, was a qualification for Diſcipleſhip, more immediately requiſite in thoſe Ages; but 'tis as true, that in bigger or leſs proportion, the words of our Lord are applicable to all, <hi>If a Man will not take up his Croſs and follow me, he cannot be my Diſciple.</hi> Whoever will imitate the Life of the bleſſed Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, <hi>who went about doing good,</hi> muſt reſolve to content himſelf with his own Integrity, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe Cenſure, to digeſt the Ingratitude of Man, and vanquiſh and weather thoſe Enmities which a ſteddy adherence to Truth and Juſtice, and much more a Zeal for reclaiming Vice, or reviving de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed Religion, will often create him; he muſt ſhrink at no Toil or Hardſhip which an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Action will put him to, nor muſt he be diſcouraged by thoſe Baffles or Diſappointments which he will often ſuffer in his moſt Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Deſigns. In one word, he muſt always have in his Thoughts the Words of our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>In the World you ſhall have Tribulation,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97899:13"/>but in me ye ſhall have Peace; but be of good comfort, I have overcome the World:</hi> i. e. he muſt propoſe to himſelf no Peace but from Religion; nor any Comfort from the World, but from the Conqueſt of it. This, you'l ſay, is a hard Leſſon, who can hear it? Not ſo hard neither; for where Affliction dwells, there the Spirit of God and Glory dwells too. Trials refine and raiſe the Faith and Courage of a true Chriſtian, and the overflowing of holy Pleaſure, that Joy unſpeakable and full of Glory in St. <hi>Peter,</hi> do ever and anon compenſate the Toils and Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of his Warfare; and a gracious God has provided Supports and Incouragements proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his Neceſſities; which is the laſt thing I am to ſpeak to.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly, The Motives to this Duty. The firſt of which is, <hi>We are encompaſſed with a Cloud of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes:</hi> without conſidering whether this Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion do ſuppoſe departed Saints Spectators and Judges of our Race here below, what I am to remark from it is, That the Apoſtle lays before us their Examples as undeniable Proof of this Truth, that there does <hi>no Temptation befal us, but what is common to men,</hi> and what has been conquer'd by them too. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> has demonſtrated this from the Old Teſtament, and <hi>we</hi> may demonſtrate it from the New. The Primitive Times were as bright for their Vertue, as their Miracles, and made as many Proſelytes by the one as by the other: How triumphant did then the Strength of Faith, the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97899:13"/>Ardours of Zeal, and the Tenderneſs of Charity appear. 'Twas as much difficulty then to reſtrain the Flights of Faith, and Tranſports of Love within the Bounds of Chriſtian Prudence, as to enkindle them now to any degrees of Decency. Then indeed the Juſt did live by Faith, they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged themſelves to be Strangers, and Pilgrims upon Earth, and ſought no Country but a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly one; then indeed they followed after Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs with that Reſolution and Impetuoſity, which ſhewed, that they did really believe they contended for a Crown and Kingdom: But now, alas! our Love of this World vies with their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of it, and our Contempt of Heaven, with their Paſſion for it: Now carnal Prudence eats up our Zeal; Faction conſumes our Charity; the Luſt of the Eye, and the Pride of Life deforms our Mortification; diſpirits our Devotion; and every little blaſt of Oppoſition overthrows our Faith. The Atheiſt digs up the Foundations, and the Looſe and Immoral demoliſh the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructures; the one denies the Truth, and the other the Power of our Chriſtian Faith; in one word, we have degenerated to that degree, that there needs as many Miracles to revive and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the Life and Spirit of Religion among us, as ever God has wrought to preſerve the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Profeſſion of it; and were there not a few Names among us dear to Heaven, I perſwade my ſelf, God could no more endure our Vices, than we their Reformation; and do you think now that in the Day of the Revelation of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97899:14"/>Judgment of God, when he ſhall render to every Man according to his Works, it will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to preſent him with Excuſes, inſtead of good Works; to urge the Temptation of the World and the Frailties of Nature inſtead of conquering them; to plead the Hypocriſie of Pretenders, and the Immorality of this or that Eccleſiaſtick, that is, the Vices of the Bad, inſtead of imitating the Vertues of the Good; Alas, a Cloud of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes will be produced to baffle this Empty So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſtry, and refute theſe poor Shifts; and then thoſe Examples which could not here enkindle and excite your Vertue will ſhame and reproach your Vice, and what could not reform, will then ſerve to condemn you. But never may this prove the Portion of any one here, but that Crown which is my ſecond Motive.</p>
            <p>Had there been any thing more dazling upon Earth then Royalty, the Spirit of God would have deſcribed the Felicity of Heaven by it; but ſince, there is not, he is content to call the Reward of Righteouſneſs a Crown; the State of the Glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Kingdom, and themſelves Kings and Prieſts to God for ever: But let not this Metaphor ſerve to debaſe our Notion of that State. This is no Kingdom of ſecret Fears and ſplendid Troubles, of wakeful Cares, and glittering Dangers: No, 'tis a Kingdom of Philoſophy and Love, of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Righteouſneſs, of Beauty and Perfection, of Joy and Triumph, of Tranquility and Reſt; not bred like that of the Ambitious, ſometimes
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97899:14"/>either by Satiety, Diſappointments, or an Increaſe of Years, but reſulting purely from Security and Extaſie. In one word, As God is his own Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſo next to that, which reſults from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of him, every one of the Bleſſed will be a Kingdom to himſelf, being an Image of God drawn in little. And yet after all this, how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle is it of Heaven that we yet know; It's Joys, for ought I know, are as boundleſs as the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of God from whence they flow. Ages may run by, while we each day ſurvey new Scenes of Wonders, and taſte each day new Worlds of Pleaſures. Ah! I cannot wonder that ſuch as were poſſeſſed with the Belief and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of this State, were willing to quit <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopotamia</hi> or an <hi>Egypt</hi> for an Heaven, Nets and Fiſher-Boats for Crowns and Kingdoms, Trifles for Treaſure, Moments for an Eternity. Ah! did not Luſt ſully the Idea of Heaven; did not ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Infidelity undermine our Belief of it, what Dangers, what Difficulties ſhould we not defie in order to ſecure it? Did doing Good expoſe us to as many Reproaches from without, as doing Evil doth from within? were the ſtate of the Righteous as uneaſie as that of the Wicked, who are <hi>as the troubled Sea</hi> when it cannot reſt; yet what would not a Man do, what would he not ſuffer, were his Soul fired with the Belief and Hopes of ſuch a Heaven? How much more fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and active would Zeal be than Ambition? how much more wakeful and indefatigable Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity than Luſt or Covetouſneſs, Revenge or Envy,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97899:15"/>(Ah! with what Tranſport would Man pour out his Time, his Treaſure, his Strength on this one Deſign of Doing Good) had he but a Heaven al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in his Eye?</p>
            <p>Let us then, that we may neither ſhrink, nor tire through any Difficulties or Hazards which may attend us in this Race of Doing Good, look up daily unto Jeſus, till our Faith be turned into Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and make Heaven our Meditation, till God make it our Reward: To whom be Glory for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:97899:15"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Several Books publiſhed by Dr.</hi> Lucas <hi>Vicar of St.</hi> Stephens Coleman-ſtreet, <hi>and ſold by</hi> Samuel Smith <hi>at the</hi> Prince<hi>'s</hi> Arms <hi>in St.</hi> Paul<hi>'s Church-yard,</hi> 1692.</head>
            <p>PRactical Chriſtianity: Or an Account of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs which the Goſpel enjoyns, with Motives to it, and the Remedies it propoſes againſt Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, with a Prayer concluding each diſtinct Duty, in <hi>Octavo</hi> 1685. Price 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>— Enquiry after Happineſs, in ſeveral Parts, Vol. 1. in <hi>Octavo.</hi> The Second Edition, Corrected and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged 1692. Price 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>— The true Notion of Humane Life: or, A Second Part of the Enquiry after Happineſs. In <hi>Octavo,</hi> 1690. Price 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>— The Duty of Apprentices and Servants. 1. The Parents Duty how to Educate their Children that they may be fit to be employed and truſted. 2. What preparation is needful for ſuch as enter into Service; with ſome Rules to be obſerved by them how to make a wiſe and happy choice of a Service. 3. Their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Service towards God, their Maſter and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; with ſuitable Prayers to each Duty; and ſome Directions peculiarly to Servants for the worthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the <hi>Holy Sacrament.</hi> Publiſhed for the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of Families. In <hi>Octavo.</hi> Price 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>— A Sermon Preached at the Funeral of Mr. <hi>Thomas Lamb, July</hi> 23. 1686. Price 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>— A Sermon Preached at the Aſſizes held at <hi>Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham</hi> in <hi>Suſſex, Aug.</hi> 23. 1691. Price 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:97899:16"/>
            <p>— Chriſtian Thoughts for every Day of the Month, with a Prayer, wherein is repreſented the Nature of Unfeigned Repentance, and of perfect Love towards God. In Twelves. Price 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>— Devotion and Charity: In a Diſcourſe before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Court of Aldermen, with the Governours of the Hoſpitals of <hi>London,</hi> on <hi>Wedneſday</hi> in the <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi>-week, at St. <hi>Bridget</hi>'s Church, being the 30th of <hi>March,</hi> 1692.</p>
            <p>—The Plain Man's Guide to Heaven; containing firſt his Duty towards God, ſecondly towards his Neighbour, with proper Prayers, Meditations, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jaculations; deſigned chiefly for the Country-man, Trades-man, Labourer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In Twelves, 1692. Price 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Thomas Manningham</hi>'s Sermon about Publick Worſhip, Preached before the Queen on <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the 23th of <hi>March,</hi> 1691/2.</p>
            <p>The Wiſdom of God manifeſted in the Works of the Creation. In two Parts. <hi>Viz.</hi> The Heavenly Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, Elements, Meteors, Foſſils, Vegetables, Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals, (Beaſts, Birds, Fiſhes, and Inſects) more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in the Body of the Earth, its Figure, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Conſiſtency, and in the admirable Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of the Bodies of Man, and other Animals, as alſo in their Generation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>John Ray</hi> Fellow of the <hi>Royal Society.</hi> In <hi>Octavo.</hi> 1692.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:97899:16"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
